Finding Aid for The Frick Collection Central Files, 1932-1936 TFC.0400.010
The Frick Collection/Frick Art Reference Library Archives
- Central Files, 1932-1933
  - Frick Art Reference Library, 1932-1933 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Includes one-page summary of 1922-1929 Library minutes regarding Helen Clay Frick's contributions to the Frick Art Reference Library, a rough sketch of the Reading Room, suggestions from the Library staff for the new Library building, and a list of Library expenditures, 1924-1932.
  - Frick Art Reference Library - Agreements, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Contains copy of June 16, 1933 agreement between The Frick Collection and the Frick Art Reference Library and an executed copy of the December 30, 1933 Memorandum of Agreement between The Frick Collection and the Frick Art Reference Library.
  - Frick, Mr. Childs [Trustee], 1932-1933 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    Contains information about material salvaged from the Frick residence.
  - Frick, Mr. Childs [Trustee] - Suggestions with Regard to Plans, 1932 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    Includes "Alternate scheme favored by Mr. Frick to accent the importance of the main picture gallery and to restrict the proposed adjacent gallery to entrance foyer proportions."
  - Frick, Miss Helen C. [Trustee], 1932-1933 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    Primarily contains copies of letters sent to Helen Clay Frick from Clapp, with some letters sent by Miss Frick and typewritten summaries of their conversations. Includes May 10, 1933 list of Miss Frick's comments about the plans for each room in the Collection and Library. Also includes discussion of material salvaged from the Frick residence to be used in the Library.
  - F - Miscellaneous, 1932-1933 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    Floorola Company
    Forbes, Edward W. [Fogg Art Museum]
  - Griggs, Maitland F. [Trustee], 1932-1933 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Guaranty Trust Company of New York, 1932-1933 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Guaranty Trust Company of New York - Statements [2 folders], 1931-1933 (Box 4, Folder 15-16)
  - G - Miscellaneous, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    Garnett, Porter
    Greene, Belle da Costa [Morgan Library] - Re tentative rules and regulations.
  - Hammond, John Henry [The Frick Collection Counsel], 1932-1933 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    Contains correspondence concerning real estate (10-12 East 71st Street), tax exemption, insurance, and building codes. Includes November 23, 1933 agreement between the Collection and the Library to split costs of lighting, heating and air conditioning.
  - Havemeyer, Horace [Trustee], 1932-1933 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Hines, Walker D. [Trustee], 1932-1933 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Holmes Electric Protective Co., 1932-1934 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    Re watchmen system contracted by the Collection, including installation and service agreement.
  - Hook & Hastings Company, 1933-1934 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    Potential contractor for removing and storing organ.
  - H - Miscellaneous, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    Hale, Mr.
    Heydt, Charles O.
    Holroyd, John
    Huntington Art Gallery - Contains attendance figures and a September, 1933 report by Frederick Mortimer Clapp on conditions at the museum and alterations made.
  - Insurance, undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Inventories, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    Contains inventories of Collection second floor, Guest Rooms #1-4, and Guest Room on third floor. Also includes list of paintings in Miss Frick's office and Students' Room in Library.
  - Inventory - Daily Inspection (Made under Mr. Naughton's Direction), 1932-1933 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
    Contains general count of specific types of objects in each room.
  - Inventory - Vault (Mr. Naughton's Notes), 1933 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    Contains lists and notes re items moved to vault during construction. Items include paintings, bronzes, Boucher panels, porcelains, and decorative items. Includes lists of items, as well as room by room inventory of items moved.
  - J - Miscellaneous, 1933 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    Jonas, Edouard
    Jurist, Mrs. Louis
  - K - Miscellaneous, 1932-1933 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    Knight, J. M. & Son, Engineers & Contractors
    Knoedler, M. & Co. - Re cleaning and preservation of The Frick Collection paintings.
    Kraft Tile Company
  - Lighting - Original House, 1914 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    Contains four-page list of lighting fixtures by Caldwell & Co., with estimates of cost and 28 small, detailed pencil drawings of each type of fixture. Original transferred to Henry Clay Frick Furnishings Files; folder contains photocopy of document.
  - L - Miscellaneous, 1933 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    Lake, Herbert Hallen - Contains March 19, 1933 letter from Charles Hall Rosefield and Herbert Hallen Lake, who worked on original construction of No. 10 East 71st Street, built for Dr. J. B. Clemens by C. P. H. Gilbert.
    Lee, Albert R. & Co. Inc.
    Lewis, Llywellyn W. - John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s "consultant builder, architect and owner's representative."
  - Manhattan Storage & Warehouse Company, 1932-1933 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    Company considered for art storage before decision to store art works in vault during construction.
  - Mellon, Andrew W. [Trustee], 1932-1933 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Memoranda on Plans [4 folders], 1932-1933 (Box 5, Folder 10-13)
    Contains short typed and handwritten memos of points to discuss, questions raised, to do lists, and telephone and conversation messages to Clapp. Often contain daily details of renovation.
  - Memoranda on Plans - Mr. Clapp's Notes [3 folders], 1932-1933 (Box 5, Folder 14-16)
    Among the topics covered are the construction of architectural models, which paintings to hang in the Oval Room, placement of the Boucher Room, the organ, construction of a vault, salvage materials, the size of the Library, air conditioning, and the organ. Also mentioned is the bust of Lorenzo, Houdon's Cagliostro, condition of the Corot paintings, Vermeer's Artist in His Studio, and the possibility of purchasing the Mackay Sassettas.
  - Memoranda on Plans - F. M. Clapp and L. W. Eisinger [Clerk of the Works], 1933 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Includes discussion of indexing fittings and fixtures at Frick residence before demolition, the organ, protection of the velvet in the West Gallery, salvage, construction of Frick Collection photographic department on the third floor, and the cornerstone for the Library.
  - Memoranda on Plans - F. M. Clapp and W. J. Naughton [Custodian], 1932-1933 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    Walnut mantel and over mantel paneling formerly of 640 Fifth Avenue mentioned.
  - Memoranda on Plans - Mr. Eisinger's Notes [Clerk of the Works], 1933 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    Re friezes in Mrs. and Miss Frick's rooms, organ, telephone service for the Collection and Library, Library book stack requirements, and air conditioning.
  - Memoranda - L. W. Eisinger [Clerk of the Works] and W. J. Naughton [Custodian], 1933 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    Contains list of fixtures to be photographed by Alfred Cook, and Miss Frick's handwritten comments on desired disposition of a list of wood paneling and ceiling salvage.
  - Memoranda - Rough Notes on Weekly Conferences, 1933 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Milliken, Henry O. (architect), 1933 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    Architect. Most memos and correspondence concern the salvage of Collection materials, including stone work, mirrors, medicine cabinets, iron gates and fences, balustrades, spandrels, statues, marble columns, and wall fountains.
  - Moorhead, William S. (Moorhead & Knox, Pittsburgh), 1933 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    Re contracts between the Collection and Library for utilities.
  - Morgan & Brother [storage warehouse], 1932-1933 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    Warehouse considered for storage of Collection art prior to decision to build basement vault.
  - Morgan, Junius S. [Trustee], 1932-1933 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Museums, 1933 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    Contains list of museums and their executive structures.
  - M - Miscellaneous, 1932-1933 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    M & S Stile Co.
    Magnuson, Beatrice A.
    Manning, Ethelwyn [Frick Art Reference Library Librarian]
    Martin, Ira W. [Frick Art Reference Library Photographer]
    McClintock, Gilbert S.
    McCormick, Robert R.
    Meriden Gravure
    Metropolitan Museum of Art
    Metropolitan Refining Co., Inc.
    Miller, Charles D. - Re 10-12 East 71st Street.
    Moorehead, Warren K. [Phillips Academy]
    Municipal Art Society
    Murphy, Grayson M. P.
  - Naughton, W. J. [Custodian], 1932-1933 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Newspaper Releases Regarding Collection, 1933 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - N - Miscellaneous, 1931-1933 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    National City Bank of New York
    New York Bureau of Fire Underwriters - Re inspection.
    New York Edison Company
    New York Steam Corporation
    New York Telephone Company
    Notice of meeting - Committee on Organization and Policy, June 10, 1932.
  - Organ - Future Possible Changes, 1933 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - O - Miscellaneous, 1932 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    Overholt, Karl F.
  - Photographic Departments [2 folders], 1932-1933 (Box 6, Folder 17-18)
    Related to space planning, layout and equipment for The Frick Collection photographic department. Contains brochure, "The Photographic Department of a Modern Museum," Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1932, as well as flyers from photographic equipment suppliers.
  - Plans, 1932-1933 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    Contains correspondence about plans.
  - Pope, John Russell [architect] [4 folders], 1932-1933 Feb. (Box 6, Folder 20-23)
    Includes discussion of cost estimates, comparison of areas of present and proposed Library building, and a response from Pope to a congratulatory letter from Frederick Mortimer Clapp re laying the cornerstone of the National Archives.
  - Pope, John Russell [architect] [10 folders], 1933 Mar.-Dec. (Box 7, Folder 1-10)
    Topics covered include the organ console space; the passageway between the Collection and Library; telautograph vs. pneumatic tubes for the Library; a proposed book conveyor between the Library and the Collection; the vault; skylights for the Oval Room, East Gallery and Lecture Room; the Lochoff fresco; the Collection and Library main entrance doors; and the layout of Helen Clay Frick's office area at the Library. Includes a list of decisions about the Library made by Miss Frick, and a list of salvaged material and its disposition, both dated September 19, 1933. A December 26, 1933 memo notes that the fireplace, book alcoves and doors of the Library penthouse rest room are "to follow closely the Fiskdale Room, Boston Museum of Fine Arts." June 26, 1933 sample key tags removed - stored in Box D.
  - Pope, John Russell [architect] - Estimates on Construction, 1933 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    Oversize sheets removed - stored in Box A.
  - Pope, John Russell [architect] - Minutes of Weekly Conferences [3 folders], 1933 Jan.-Aug. (Box 7, Folder 12-14)
    Among the topics covered are elevators, the location of mechanical equipment, skylights, the design of the Lecture Room, reuse of the bowling alley paneling in the Library, the vacuum system, projection equipment, a second floor passageway between the Collection and the Library, design of the Enamels Room, air conditioning, resetting of first floor Office mantel in new Trustees' Room, and photography of construction progress by Alfred Cook.
  - Pope, John Russell [architect] - Minutes of Weekly Conferences, 1933 Sep.-Dec. (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Pope, John Russell [architect] - Reports in Connection with Plans for Collection and Library, 1932-1933 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    Includes January 18, 1932 Architect's Report on The Frick Collection; March 12, 1932 resume of suggested alterations and additions to the Library and the Collection; as well as reports concerning an auditorium on the second floor, a list of Miss Frick's requirements for the Library, plans for the Enamels Room, a comparative table of gross floor areas and equipment capacity for the present and proposed library, a visit to the Marshall Field House on East 70th Street, existing stacks in the Library, the treatment of Gallery 214 (Miss Frick's bedroom), and the lighting of the new galleries.
  - Pope, John Russell [architect] - Wood Paneling, 1932 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Powers Regulator Company - Reports, 1932 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    Re inspections of air conditioning in vault.
  - Printing, 1933 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    Contains solicitation letters from printing companies. Includes portfolio of samples from Meriden Gravure Company.
  - Projection Apparatus and Television, 1933 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    Contains April 20, 1933 copy letter from Alfred N. Goldsmith re audio-visual requirements for Lecture Room, including television, telephone, motion pictures, three-dimensional motion pictures and color organ effects.
  - P - Miscellaneous, 1932-1933 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    Paramount Pictures Distributing Corporation
    Plans - Includes John Russell Pope and Delano & Aldrich schedule of plans (August 15, 1932), and 1933 list of new and old plumbing fixtures and trimming.
    Pullman Company
  - Real Estate, 1932 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    Contains solicitation letter from Howard LeC. Roome, Inc.
  - Remington Rand Inc., 1933 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    Re equipment rentals and orders: typewriters, ribbons, trays, and safe cabinet.
  - Reports of Organizing Director, 1933 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    Contains two summary reports: January 12 to April 14, 1933 and April 13 to June 14, 1933. Topics covered include construction of the vault, inventories, the purchase of 10-12 East 71st Street, the first set of estimates for the project, air conditioning, insurance, security, and the small catalogue.
  - Reports regarding Plans for Opening The Frick Collection [2 folders], 1932-1933 (Box 8, Folder 11-12)
    Includes the following reports, as well as numerous others:
    Report of the Present Status of Plans for Opening The Frick Collection, March 2, 1932
    Report on the space requirements of the Frick Art Reference Library, March 14, 1932
    Condensed report of decisions regarding the Collection and Library and outlines of John Russell Pope's and Delano & Aldrich's plans, March 23, 1932
    Report on Taylor property as solution of space requirements of the Library, May 6, 1932
    Report on the space requirements of the Library for 40-50 years, May 12, 1932
    Rules and Regulations of The Frick Collection, June 26, 1932
    Report on the Library plans submitted by Pope's office, September 28, 1932
    Report on plans for alterations and additions to the Collection as submitted by John Russell Pope, October 25, 1932
    "Functions of the Organizing Director" job description, January 4, 1933
  - Requests for Admission [2 folders], 1932-1933 (Box 8, Folder 13-14)
    Re admission of Lord and Lady Reading in November, 1932 and Count Colloredo-Mansfeld in January, 1933. All other requests denied.
  - Requests for Information re The Frick Collection, 1932-1933 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Requests for Permission to Reproduce Pictures in The Frick Collection, 1932-1933 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Requests for Photographs of Articles in The Frick Collection, 1932-1933 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Rockefeller, John D., Jr. [Trustee], 1932-1933 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    Contains Rockefeller's correspondence with Clapp, who was on an extended vacation/sick leave, reporting on the progress of the construction.
  - Roofing and Repairs, 1931-1932 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    Contains November 14, 1932 roof inspection report.
  - R - Miscellaneous, 1932-1933 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    Repairs, Building - Miller-Druck Co., Inc. re courtyard vase.
    Reeves, Daniel Inc.
    Rhode Island School of Design - Re air conditioning.
  - Skylight Protection, 1933 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    Related to New York City Building Department requirements of wire guards/mesh in certain types of skylights.
  - Snead & Company, 1933 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    Contractor for Frick Art Reference Library book stacks.
  - Statements - Construction Account - U.S. Trust Co., 1933 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Statements - Frick Collection Custodian Account, 1931-1932 (Box 8, Folder 24)
    Oversize statements stored in Box A.
  - Statements - Frick Collection House Account, 1933-1934 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Stonework - Pointing and Preservation, 1931-1933 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Storage, 1932-1933 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    Re storage of art works during renovation in warehouse vs. vault constructed in basement. Includes June 27, 1932 John Russell Pope report, "A Report on Proposals for the Safe-Keeping of The Frick Collection during Alterations and Additions to the Building." Also contains information re total bulk of objects in cubic feet, size of Fragonard panels, and list of paintings that are too large to go on the third floor, with sizes, both with and without frames.
  - Syska & Hennessy [consulting engineers], 1933 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Syska & Hennessy [consulting engineers] - Contract for Engineering Service, 1933 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Syska & Hennessy [consulting engineers] - Copies of Letters, 1933 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    Contains letters copied to John Russell Pope and Marc Eidlitz & Son.
  - S - Miscellaneous, 1932-1933 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    Schaub-Koch, Emile
    Scrapbook Guild
    Sheffield Farms Company, Inc.
    Sherron, George A. [Rhinelander Real Estate Company] - Re Witherbee house.
    Smith, Frank C., Jr. - Contains letter of introduction for Frederick Mortimer Clapp from Helen Clay Frick.
    Sizer, Theodore [Yale University Gallery of Fine Arts]
    Southworth Press.
    Stechert, G. E. & Co.
    Stone, Benjamin H. [Worcester Art Museum]
    Stout, George L. [Fogg Art Museum] - Re air conditioning, temperature and humidity.
  - Telautograph Corporation, 1933 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    Communications system that enabled handwritten messages to appear on the paper roll of each receiving instrument within a network.
  - Trustees - Minutes of Meetings [2 folders] [RESTRICTED FILE], 1932-1933 (Box 9, Folder 8-9)
  - T - Miscellaneous, 1932-1933 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    Taylor, Francis Henry [Worcester Art Museum]
    Telephone calls
    Tiffany & Co. - Instructed not to wind clocks at the Collection.
    Tingle, Gladys G.
  - United States Trust Company, 1932-1933 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - U - Miscellaneous, 1932-1933 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    Underwood Typewriter
  - Vault, 1933 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    List of items, including paintings, mantel sets, sculpture, bronzes, and furniture, to be moved to the vault. Includes measurements (height, width, depth, and cubic inches and feet).
  - Watson, Thomas E. (Marc Eidlitz & Son, Inc. - Superintendent), 1933 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Western Union, 1932-1933 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    Contains copies of telegrams sent.
  - Westinghouse Electric & Manufacturing Company, 1933 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - W - Miscellaneous, 1932-1933 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    Water meters
    Weeks, Frank A., Manufacturing Company
    Witherbee, Mrs. Frank S.
    Wittenmeier Machinery Company
  - X-Y-Z - Miscellaneous, 1932-1933 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    Yaeger & Company
    York Ice Machinery Corporation
    Young, T. J.
- Central Files, 1934
  - Index, 1934 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Accounts, 1934 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Aeolian-Skinner Organ Company, 1934 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    Re movable platform, conduit work, and new console.
  - Air Conditioning, 1933-1934 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    Re cooling tower, general installation and operating decisions.
  - American Association of Museums - Bulletins, 1934 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - American District Telegraph Company (Electric Protection Services), 1934 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Annunciator System for Collection, 1934 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Applications for Employment [2 folders] [RESTRICTED FILE], 1933-1934 (Box 10, Folder 8-9)
  - A - Miscellaneous, 1934 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    Allegheny Metal
    Almirall & Company, Inc. - Re testing of air supply registers and nozzles.
    Avinoff, Dr. Andrey [Carnegie Museum]
  - Baker, George F. [Trustee], 1934 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Bludworth, Inc. [contractor for work on organ], 1934 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    Re organ sound chamber and additional amplifier.
  - Booklets, 1934 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Bookstacks for Library [2 folders], 1933-1934 (Box 10, Folder 14-15)
    Snead & Co. was contracted to provide book shelves for Library. Re shelf specifications, location, placement in new building, electric wiring in stacks, color, and cost. Metal samples of shelf material removed and stored in Box D.
  - Bookstacks for Library - Plans, 1934 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Brewer-Ward Co., Inc., 1934 (Box 10, Folder 17)
    Re office supplies, including Collection stationery.
  - B - Miscellaneous, 1934 (Box 10, Folder 18)
    Balcom, H. G. [consulting engineer]
    Baumstone, Teina
    Bowman, Dr.
    Bridge, James H. - Contains stock mailer sent to him at The Frick Collection address.
    Buildings, Department of
  - Cabinet Work, 1934 (Box 10, Folder 19)
    Includes outline of cabinet and wood work specifications room-by-room for the Collection and Library and, a summary of the contracts awarded. Cabinet work discussed includes woodwork, paneling, wainscot, doorways, ceilings, doors, trim, ornaments, and painting.
  - Charles Paneling for Librarian's Room, 1934 (Box 10, Folder 20)
    Re Old English paneling from Charles of London. Contains blueprint of doors.
  - Clapp, Frederick Mortimer, 1934 (Box 10, Folder 21)
    Re subcontract for carving of lunette over Library entrance, Library woodwork, Library furniture, and Reading Room table lamps. Includes an August 10, 1934 summary of a meeting with John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Clippings, 1934 (Box 10, Folder 22)
    Includes clippings on the opening of the Frick Art Reference Library, the Frick Collection suit re tax exemption, and the delay in the opening of the Frick Collection.
  - Committee on Organization and Policy [2 folders], 1934 Jan.-Apr. (Box 10, Folder 23-24)
    Members: John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Childs Frick, and Maitland Griggs. Topics covered include air conditioning, sump pumps, brick facing of the Library, the Widener house window lattice, the vacuum cleaning system, insurance, the Library elevator, a fountain on the Library terrace, heating and ventilating systems, shoring and support of the west wall of the Garden Court, organ sound transmission, and roofing.
  - Committee on Organization and Policy [2 folders], 1934 May-Dec. (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
    Topics covered include roofing and skylights, budget overruns for the Library, the Reading Room ceiling, finish of the Garden Court panels, new organ console, lighting in galleries, sidewalks, and the fountain in the Garden Court pool.
  - Committee on Organization and Policy - Minutes and Reports of Meetings, 1934 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    Topics covered include Miss Frick's dissatisfaction with the lunette over the Library's entrance, the hanging of artworks in the Oval Room as well as other galleries, colors to be used in new rooms (it was decided to wait until the paintings were selected for each room), the location of Mr. Frick's bust, the quality of woodwork (Hayden and Company), and the replacement of Mr. Eisinger as Clerk of Works due to health reasons with Mr. I.D. Matthew.
  - Contractors, 1934 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    Contains solicitation letters.
  - Cooling Tower, 1934 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - C - Miscellaneous, 1934 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    Cahill, Mrs. A. A.
    Columbia University
  - Designs for Monograms - Collection and Library, 1933-1934 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    Contains correspondence and drawings related to Henry Clay Frick monogram for the Library entrance. Oversize photostats of drawings stored in Box C.
  - D - Miscellaneous, 1934 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    Dakin, Howard
    Dietzgen, Eugene Co.
    Duparquet Huot & Moneuse Co. - Re equipment for Library kitchen.
  - Eidlitz, Marc & Son [general contractors] [3 folders], 1934 (Box 11, Folder 9-11)